The plants on alien planets could be any
color. So, how do we know what to look
for? If we look at Earth, we see a ton
[music] of green because the plants here
use a molecule called chlorophyll that
absorbs red and blue wavelengths and
reflects back green as it turns sunlight
into energy. But, the farther away we
get in space, that tiny bit of green
gets harder and harder to see. We
wouldn't pick up green forests on a
planet several light-years away. So, we
need to look for something much
stronger. Plants can't absorb all the
sunlight for energy, they'd fry. So, to
keep cool, they also reflect a type of
light just past what our eyes can see,
near-infrared light, a lot [laughter] of
it. And scientists call this huge jump
the vegetation red edge. And to see it,
we have special lenses. And if you look
at Earth through one of those, our
forests don't look green at all, they
glow bright white. So, no matter what
color an alien forest is, theoretically,
it's going to absorb some amount of
visible light for energy and reflects
back a ton of other light to stay cool.
So, scientists scan the light spectrum
for signs of a giant leap. And if we
find that, it could mean that something
down there is very much alive. Then we
need secondary evidence. And to see what
that [music] is, subscribe.